# J. Brent Cleland

615-275-7637 | bcleland@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/brent-cleland | github.com/jbcleland

# SKILLS & PROFICIENCIES

Data Analysis, SQL, Python, Excel, Tableau, Power BI, GitHub, Kanban, Agile

# EDUCATIONAL BACKGROUND

### NASHVILLE SOFTWARE SCHOOL

Data Analytics Bootcamp

Full-time program using statistical reasoning through hands-on training in Excel, Python, SQL, Tableau, and Power BI with a focus on data storytelling, building reports, and creating dashboards.

# **UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH CAROLINA**BA English

# PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Enthusiastic team player who passionately enjoys bringing data to life utilizing visualizations and key data points found via research to drive action. Leveraging 20+ years using data in various industries to communicate with their audience. Looking to partner with diverse teams to collaborate and impact change.

# **PROJECTS**

## APP TRADER (POSTGRES SQL, EXCEL):

Cleaned, explored, and analyzed data to gain insight from apps that are available from Apple App Store and Google Play Store. Visualized and presented data-based investment recommendations on the top 10 most profitable apps in both app stores, provided further details and insights based on genre, price ranges, and content ratings of apps to increase profitability.

# LAHMAN BASEBALL (POSTGRES SQL):

Analysis of baseball statistics through a database consisting of > 25 tables using SQL queries such as JOINS (LEFT,INNER, OUTER), CTEs, windows functions to identify various trends within the data.

# PARIS-ROUBAIX (EXCEL, TABLEAU):

Research and visually told the history of the 2nd oldest of the monuments in the spring classics of road bike racing. Used tableau to visually explain and showcase several interesting facts about this race.

# WORK EXPERIENCE

### NASHVILLE SOFTWARE SCHOOL | Jan 2022 - Present

# Data Analyst Apprentice

Intensive part-time bootcamp focusing on data analytics fundamentals and problem solving. Used real-world datasets and included projects where findings were presented to stakeholders from the community.

- Analyzed data using Microsoft Excel, including utilizing pivot tables and lookups, and connected to external data sources using the PowerPivot
- Built and deployed dashboards using Tableau and PowerBI
- Wrangled data and performed exploratory data analysis using Python's pandas library
- Created data visualizations using matplotlib and seaborn
- Retrieved and analyzed data using PostgreSQL
- Source code version control with Git/GitHub
- · Project management/tracking with GitHub project boards and issue tracking

### RICOH USA | 2017-2022

Director of Customer Communications Management

A leading provider of document management solutions, IT services, communication services, commercial and industrial printing, digital cameras, and industrial systems.

- Responsible for developing complex print solutions.
- Provide leadership to document composition developers (Quadient, Inspire, Transformation Uluro), reporting team, project managers. consulting teams, and Disaster Recovery Services
- Partner with Sales Team to Deliver Poignant custom solutions
- Solution, Develop and Design Architecture solutions for customer to assist critical communication prerequisites
- Mitigated and anticipated process gaps and develop preventative measures
- Initiated and executed process improvement initiatives
- Routinely involved in Project Management and Reengineering concepts

#### RICOH USA • 2015-2017

# **Principal Consultant**

- Assessed, documented, and identified opportunities
- Authored and delivered Statement of Works for supported solutions.
- Responsible for pricing and estimating costs associated with services offerings.

#### PARRIS PRINTING • 2014-2015

### **Director Data Services**

A full-service provider of design, strategy, printing, mailing, and fulfillment within a secure HIPAA and HITECH compliant environment.

Provided Business Intelligence Data for critical operations while serving as a Subject Matter Expert on system enhancements. Assisted Sales Team with Proof of Concepts and implemented systematic controls.

#### AFFINION BENEFITS GROUP • 2007-2014

# **Director Production Control**

A leading provider of marketing and insurance administration expertise to financial institutions and other partners. Now known as Tenerity.

- Provided leadership to document composition developers, data analysts, reporting team, and quality control analysts.
- Oversaw maintenance of Data Warehouse, Data Flow of 100M+ records annually.
- Managed Disaster Recovery program.
- Routinely involved in Project Management and Reengineering concepts.